<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The man of peace: or, The glorious appearance of the great God in his people, rising as a man of war, to waste the Assyrian, that is, the mighty oppressor, or enemy to our peace. Being a second olive-leaf, springing 1. To heal the nation, or people of the land. 2. To humble the princes, or people of the Lord. 3. To heighten the spirits of the English, above all the nations about, to break them, or bring them in (with us) to the government of Jesus. By William Erbery.</title>
            <author>Erbery, William, 1604-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84074</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865947</idno>
  <idno type="VID">118203</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240937658</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E729_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206845</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865947</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865947e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118203)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E729[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The man of peace: or, The glorious appearance of the great God in his people, rising as a man of war, to waste the Assyrian, that is, the mighty oppressor, or enemy to our peace. Being a second olive-leaf, springing 1. To heal the nation, or people of the land. 2. To humble the princes, or people of the Lord. 3. To heighten the spirits of the English, above all the nations about, to break them, or bring them in (with us) to the government of Jesus. By William Erbery.</title>
                  <author>Erbery, William, 1604-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by James Cottrel.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"1. To heal .. (with us) to" connected by left curly bracket.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 14"; the 4 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O.T. --  Micah V, 5-6 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Religion and politics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118203:1"/>
            <p>The Man of Peace: OR, The Glorious appearance of the great GOD in his People, RISING AS A Man of War, TO WASTE <hi>The ASSYRIAN,</hi> THAT IS, The Mighty Oppressor, OR Enemy to our Peace. BEING <hi>A second Olive-leaf,</hi> Springing
<list>
                  <item>1. To heal the Nation, or people of the Land.</item>
                  <item>2. To humble the Princes, or people of the Lord.</item>
                  <item>3. To heighten the spirits of the ENGLISH, above all the Nations about, to break them, or bring them in (with us) to</item>
               </list>
               <hi>The Government of</hi> JESUS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Erbery.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord shall go forth as a Mighty man, he shall stir up jealousie as a Man of War: he shall cry, yea roar, and prevail</hi> (or, behave himself mightily) <hi>against his enemies. I have long holden my peace, and been still, and refrained my self: now will I cry like a traveling woman; I will destroy and devour at once. I will make waste mountains and hills,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>Isai. 42.13,14,15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at LONDON, by <hi>James Cottrel.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118203:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118203:2"/>
            <div type="dedication">
               <head>For Mr. <hi>Feak,</hi> Mr. <hi>Simpson,</hi> and all the Members of Christs Church.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Brethren,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Spake last for the <hi>peace of the State;</hi> now I shall a word for yours (and all <hi>the Saints</hi> with you) <hi>in bonds. Heb.</hi> 13.3. This Scripture is still in force for all who are <hi>in bonds,</hi> we being of the <hi>same Body</hi> with them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Members of Christs Church,</hi> I mean the <hi>Church of the First-born</hi> written <hi>in heaven,</hi> which I hope to see <hi>on earth</hi> with you in spiritual glory; when all the <hi>scattered Saints,</hi> scattered in <hi>forms and flesh,</hi> are <hi>gathered</hi> up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to One, and <hi>One in All.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="epigraph">
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This man shall be the peace, when the Assyrian shall come into our land: and when he shall tread in our palaces, then shall we raise against him seven shepherds and eight principal men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they shall waste the land of Assyria with the sword, and the land of Nimrod in the entrances thereof. Thus shall he deliver us from the Assyrian when he cometh into our land, and when he treadeth within our borders.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Micah 5.5,6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="discourse">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall not preach, but present in haste a few Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals to your prudent and pious considerations, in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Queries and Answers following.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118203:3"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>First, what's this man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis the mighty God manifest in flesh. For as Christ in the flesh was the manifestation of God in him; so Christ in the spirit is the manifestation of God in our flesh, as in his. For as God was in Christ, and God all in all in him, without whom Christ could do nothing, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19,30. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.10. so Christ is in us, and Christ all in all, through whom we can <hi>do all things,</hi> even <hi>sit in the throne of God with him, judge An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men;</hi> yea, <hi>rule the nations with a rod of iron;</hi> then raise them and save them again. <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.4. <hi>Obad. v.</hi> 21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.3. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26,27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. <hi>Isa.</hi> 41.14,15. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.20. compared.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How is this man the Peace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. By taking <hi>mans flesh</hi> into <hi>union with God</hi> in himself, and manifesting that Union in us by the Spirit. That is, though the Spirit appear not in men as yet, nor doth manifest their union with God; yet that Man is become One with God in Christ the God-Man, is manifest by this. 1. Because he is <hi>Immanuel, God with us;</hi> not God with him onely, but God with us is Christ. 2. He shall <hi>save his people from their sins:</hi> that is, not onely <hi>his people the Jews,</hi> that Nation, but the Gentiles, or Nations, that's joy <hi>to all people;</hi> he being born not onely a childe to <hi>Ʋs,</hi> but <hi>the Saviour of the World.</hi> 3. From the worst of men Christ came according to the flesh; <hi>Rahab</hi> the harlot was his grandmother, and <hi>Manasseh</hi> the murtherer his forefather, as well as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and good <hi>Josiah:</hi> for Christ was not onely the son of <hi>Abraham</hi> the faithful, but the son of <hi>Adam</hi> the fallen. <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.1,5,10. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.38. compared. 4. All the sons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of men may therefore see themselves in God with Christ. <hi>Isa.</hi> 45.22. 5. No <hi>son of Adam,</hi> but is one with the <hi>Son of God,</hi> if men had the power to <hi>present every man in Christ,</hi> Col. 1.28.6. Not onely the <hi>Apostles,</hi> but the <hi>Poet</hi> saith, <hi>We are the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spring of God;</hi> and the Poets saying is canonized as Scripture by the <hi>Apostle: for in him we live, move, and have our being. Acts</hi> 17.28. <hi>We,</hi> that's <hi>all men,</hi> for no Saint was there present with the Apostle: and the Poet spake not of Saints, but of Men with himself; that <hi>we</hi> are his off-spring. 7. Our own Catechisms
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118203:3"/> tell us, that not any mans person, but the <hi>whole</hi> humane nature was taken up with Christ in God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This man is the Peace, not onely as our flesh is in union with God in him, but as God crucified our flesh in him, and his flesh is now crucified in us: that is, as the flesh of Christ being crucified by God and to God, became our peace, <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14.15. so this Peace is not ratified to us, till his flesh be both revealed in us, and crucified in us also to God. For though his <hi>flesh profited nothing,</hi> but the spirit that quickned and lived in it was all; yet did men look upon that flesh too much: <hi>Good Master</hi> saith one; <hi>Never man spake like this man,</hi> saith another. Therefore God did crucifie and slay that flesh to himself, made it weak as ever mans was, <hi>a worm and no man,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> might appear to be <hi>all in all.</hi> And as Christ in his greatest weakness, and lowest state of flesh, when he fainted, and feared, and cried out as a man forsaken of God, was as perfectly one with God, as when he was in high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est glory, in his mighty works of wonder, and most gracious words: so we, though troubled, tempted, sorrowful to the death, and sinking to despair, as he may yet be sure we are one with God: and though his pure flesh in us, our gifts, graces, joy, peace, and spiritual strength, be so weakned and wasted, crucified and slain, that nothing but the face of death appears without and within us; yet we, I say, even in this dead estate of flesh, are as perfectly one with the Father, and his love to us as his beloved, and our life in him as pure, as the Sons was when dying, and as ours appears to us in our highest attainments, and most heavenly enjoyments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus is This Man the Peace.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>But who is the Assyrian?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Oppressive power</hi> of man and in man.</p>
               <p>First, I say, the <hi>Oppressive power</hi> in man, is <hi>the Assyrian:</hi> that is, the weakness of the flesh, besides the strength of corruption, our infirmities, fears, faintings of spirit, spiritual desertions, and seeming forsakings of God, this doth oppress us: but then when Christ doth appear, and appear in us, as our peace, and <hi>our peace perfected in suffering,</hi> and <hi>our sufferings now become his,</hi> (for he suffers in us, and <hi>in all our afflictions he is afflicted</hi>) all this doth refresh, and fully satisfie, yea free us from the inward Assy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118203:4"/> the oppressor within being the power of flesh oppressing our spirits, or the weakness of flesh when the Spirit is ready to rise, <hi>&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 26.41. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18,23.</p>
               <p>But as there is an Oppressor in man, so the Oppressor of man is some man (or men) without, called the <hi>Assyrian,</hi> or king of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, who carries us captive, and keeps us in <hi>bondage</hi> in our spirits and states: but we shall be <hi>delivered</hi> from both, when we shall <hi>rule over our oppressors,</hi> Isai. 14.2. How shall we <hi>weak creatures rule</hi> over them? In <hi>the Lord,</hi> vers. 3. How will God give us <hi>this rule and government?</hi> By giving us a spirit to rise up, and to rejoyce over them in a Proverb, (or taunting speech, as the margin reads) vers. 4. <hi>How is the oppressor ceased, the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den city!</hi> or, the gold-thirsting city, as the Geneva renders. 'Tis our gold which they thirst after, makes them to oppress us, to come into our Land, and tread in our Palaces, as the Prophet addes, <hi>Mic.</hi> 5.6. Or the golden city is the purest and most glorious Church-state. This is gone already.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What's our land, our palaces?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis our Country, and our Court or Palaces, for both are the peoples. For as all the people are in Parliament assembled, so the <hi>palaces</hi> or <hi>court</hi> of King and Prince is theirs, though both has been kept back by the Assyrian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But how does the Assyrian come into our land? how dares he tread in our palaces?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis meerly by an <hi>oppressive power.</hi> The Lord protect our Princes from this, from all kinde of Oppression.</p>
               <p>For as <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Assyria</hi> were the onely two great Powers who kept the people of God in bondage formerly according to the Type: so in Truth <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> in this, Land were the two Powers, who kept the people of the Lord and the people of the Land from their expected and promised freedoms. For <hi>the Keepers of the Liberty of England</hi> were Keepers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and of our Liberties from us.</p>
               <p>Now thus saith the Lord, <hi>My people went down to sojourn in Egypt, and the Assyrian oppressed them without cause,</hi> Isa. 52.4 That is, the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> had some cause to keep us ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptives, because the people gave their power out of their hands
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118203:4"/>
                  <hi>freely, by common consent,</hi> as the people of God went down <hi>willingly into Egypt:</hi> but the Assyrian carried them away ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptives by force; therefore 'twas <hi>without cause he oppressed</hi> them. The Lord preserve our Princes from this also: for if they oppress us, 'tis without cause, or our consent. But This Man will deliver us, saith <hi>Micah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now therefore what have I here, saith the Lord,</hi> (What is this Power newly risen?) <hi>that my people is taken away for nought, and they that rule over them make them to howl, saith the Lord; and my Name continually every day is blasphemed? Isai.</hi> 52.5. That is the blessed Name of God will be blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med every day, and (all the day long too) continually, if his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who rule now should turn oppressors; that's the Assyrian.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then we shall raise against him seven shepherds, and eight principal men.</hi> Mic. 5.6.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How shall the people of God raise forces against the Assyrian, or Oppressive Powers of men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A. Not by power, nor by might,</hi> (or <hi>Army,</hi> saith the margin) <hi>but by my Spirit, saith the Lord.</hi> Zech. 4.6.</p>
               <p>The <hi>people of God</hi> under the King had no power nor might to resist him; but the Spirit of the Lord in them <hi>raised a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> against him, even <hi>seven shepherds and eight principal men,</hi> or Princes (as the margin reads:) for as the <hi>Commons</hi> were as the <hi>Shepherds,</hi> who stood for the Country; so the <hi>house of Lords</hi> were as the <hi>principal men,</hi> or Princes of men, which have Crowns in their Arms.</p>
               <p>Again, when <hi>a corrupt Parliament</hi> oppress'd the people, who raised up <hi>an Army</hi> first to purge, then to dissolve them? The Spirit or power of God in his people in City and Country, and in the Army too.</p>
               <p>If this <hi>third Power</hi> prove to be the Assyrian, <hi>we shall raise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him seven shepherds and eight principal men;</hi> yea a suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient strength and most perfect ability in the Lord to <hi>waste As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syria with the sword:</hi> that is, the Spirit of the Lord, and sword of his mouth, shall as surely slay them, as ever Kingly power was by the mouth of the Sword.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Land of Nimrod in the entrances thereof,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118203:5"/> v. 6. that is, the least appearance of an oppressive Kingly power.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What's the land of Nimrod that is to be wasted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Why 'tis the <hi>Kingly power, as 'tis oppressive</hi> to the people of the Lord, and to the people of the Land: not Kingly power of it self, but as 'tis oppressive to us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nimrod</hi> was the <hi>first King</hi> that ever was, and he was the king of <hi>Babel:</hi> that's a mystery, that the first king in the world should be the king of Babel, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.9,10. Therefore <hi>Babylons fall</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth <hi>the kings of the earth to weep and wail,</hi> Rev. 18.9.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Nimrod</hi> was an oppressive power he was <hi>a mighty hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before the Lord,</hi> Gen. 10.9. that's cunning and cruel to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy both man and beast. So the former Kings of <hi>England</hi> have been; not onely king <hi>James,</hi> but <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror was <hi>a mighty hunter,</hi> wasting all Hampshire to make room for his game: but God met with his son <hi>Rufus</hi> in the sport, causing a shaft aim'd at the Deer to shoot thorow the Kings heart.</p>
               <p>Again, former Kings were <hi>mighty hunters before the Lord;</hi> that is, <hi>hunters of his people,</hi> whom they persecuted to strange countries. Therefore the Kingly posterity is now hunted out of their own country also, and fain to run to and fro in forrain lands for relief.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nimrod</hi> that <hi>Kingly power</hi> has been from the beginning, and gone on in a race of oppression over the people of God: yet have these Kings, with their Nobles, Lords and Dukes, all proceeded from a cursed Pedigree.</p>
               <p>Not to speak of <hi>Nimrod</hi> any more, nor the kings of Sodom, the first that I read of the kingly power, next to the king of Shinar, that's of Babylon, and the kings about, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.1,2. I cannot but consider, that scoffing <hi>Ishmael,</hi> the son after the flesh, was the first (among the people of God) from whom <hi>kings,</hi> even <hi>twelve princes</hi> arose, who had <hi>towns and castles</hi> too. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.20. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Esau,</hi> even bloody <hi>Edom,</hi> was the first who brought forth <hi>Dukes</hi> or <hi>Nobles,</hi> Gen. 36.15. <hi>Duke Teman, duke Omar, duke Zepho,</hi> &amp;c. even <hi>twelve dukes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as the <hi>Kings</hi> of the nations were onely those who opposed the people of God in their march toward Canaan: so <hi>thirty one</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118203:5"/> are there named, one by one; <hi>The king of Jericho one, the king of Ai one, the king of Jerusalem one,</hi> &amp;c. and so all along, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a secret (that I know not) of one and one; that is, not one better then another, but all alike to the last. <hi>Josh.</hi> 12.9. to 24.</p>
               <p>And as the <hi>first King</hi> that ever God gave to his people was <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in wrath,</hi> because they were not content with the <hi>reign of God,</hi> but must have <hi>a king as other nations had,</hi> 1 Sam. 8.5,6. Hos. 13.11. so 'tis observed, that when there was no King among them, they were never better governed; yea, <hi>the shout of a king was among them</hi> when they had none, God going before them <hi>in the wilderness,</hi> though they <hi>saw not the way before them,</hi> Numb. 23.21.</p>
               <p>Therefore seeing the <hi>people of God</hi> are called <hi>The Lords anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and he <hi>reproved kings</hi> for their sake; 'tis well with those who lay no hands on his, though <hi>kings are reproved</hi> by them, <hi>Psal.</hi> 105.14. For seeing the Saints <hi>shall judge the world, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> too, that is, not onely in heavenly and spiritual things, but the Civil State also; let all men know, that this is not an aspiring to Greatness, nor envying any Power, Rule, or Government, which Christ in the Spirit will subdue, and <hi>put under his feet,</hi> (as enemies to him, and to his raign in righteousness, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24,25.) but <hi>such honour have all his Saints,</hi> as <hi>to binde their kings in chains, and their nobles in links of iron;</hi> that is, to give a right judgement of that Rule and Government which Civil Powers and Princes (especially his people) exercise in the nation. <hi>Psal.</hi> 149.8,9.</p>
               <p>There is much in this Psalm that concerns the <hi>reign of Christ</hi> and of the <hi>Saints with him on earth,</hi> (which was hinted in the <hi>Olive-leaf,</hi> p. 8.) that the Saints have the <hi>high praises of God</hi> in their mouths, and <hi>a two-edged sword in their hands,</hi> v. 6. that is, the Magistrates sword they meddle not with, but the <hi>sword of the Lord</hi> and of <hi>Gideon;</hi> which <hi>brought down the walls of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo</hi> with the <hi>sound of rams horns,</hi> and the <hi>shout of the Lords hosts,</hi> the people of God with him, <hi>Josh.</hi> 6.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>high praises of God</hi> in the Saints of the most High (in whom they rest and rejoyce) causeth the walls of worldly powers to fall before them. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.22.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their <hi>executing vengeance on the heathen,</hi> Psal. 149.7. is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118203:6"/> that which <hi>Jude</hi> speaks of in <hi>Enoch</hi>'s prophecie, where <hi>the Lord cometh with ten thousand of his Saints, to execute vengeance on all the ungodly, for all their hard speeches against him</hi> in his Saints. These <hi>ungodly ones</hi> are professors sure; for they are at the <hi>feasts of love, feeding themselves without fear, having mens persons in admiration because of advantage,</hi> or <hi>gain,</hi> Jude vers. 12, 14, 15, 16. compare.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>heathen</hi> here, are also <hi>earthly powers,</hi> or Governours, <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Nobles,</hi> whom the Saints are said to binde in chains, not by resistance, but by that restraining power of the Almighty in them, keeping those back from doing any harm to his people or nation, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Though the Gospel-Churches did never meddle with Civil matters or Magistrates, being purely Heathen then; nor since the Apostacie was it a long time lawful for spiritual Saints to intermix with Civil affairs: (for the Churches have formerly fallen by this) yet seeing we wait for <hi>a new heaven and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteousness,</hi> and this <hi>righteousness</hi> is promised to be <hi>on earth</hi> as well as in <hi>heaven;</hi> that is, in the <hi>Civil</hi> as well as the <hi>Ecclesiastick</hi> state, (for <hi>our officers shall be peace, and our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actors righteousness</hi>) therefore in the third dispensation now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, (wherein the people of God are in highest power) all things <hi>in heaven and earth</hi> shall be <hi>gathered up into Christ;</hi> not onely the <hi>Saints</hi> in common, but the <hi>State</hi> is to <hi>act in Christ, and as Christ Jesus would do to men.</hi> Therefore his Members and <hi>brethren</hi> are bold in the Lord, not to dishonour, but to admonish the highest in power, not to run on those <hi>rocks,</hi> whereon former <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Parliaments</hi> were <hi>wrackt and ruined.</hi> The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>Charybdis</hi> was their strangling (by delays) the <hi>Petitions</hi> of the <hi>fatherless and widow,</hi> of the <hi>poor</hi> &amp; <hi>oppressed ones,</hi> while they sought <hi>themselves</hi> onely. That <hi>Scylla</hi> which split the King, was his setting up <hi>the state of his Court</hi> and Courtiers, preferring none but the rich, his <hi>friends and favourites,</hi> a company of fools and flatterers, though the <hi>oppressed peeled nation</hi> were ready to perish. And yet the King had a <hi>revenue</hi> of his own to maintain his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty: the <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>gallantry</hi> of his Palace, his <hi>babies</hi> and <hi>baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles</hi> were no burden to the people.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118203:6"/>
               <p n="6">6. Seeing <hi>all the Saints</hi> have that <hi>honour</hi> in God and Christ, as <hi>to binde Kings and Nobles in chains;</hi> I hope the time is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Kings and Nobles will no more binde in chains the Saints:</hi> 1. Because of the <hi>honour</hi> that <hi>all the Saints</hi> have in God. 2. The <hi>homage</hi> that <hi>all Kings</hi> owe to God. 3. Because what <hi>Kings</hi> knew not before is now made manifest to the <hi>Saints,</hi> and to Kings. 4. Though the name of Kings be now somewhat suspicious to the Saints, (therefore an Act was made by the late Parliament, that <hi>the name of Kingly power, and that unnecessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry charge should cease</hi>) yet to me 'tis not so ominous, seeing the <hi>kings of the earth bring their glory and honour to the new Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem,</hi> Rev. 21.24. But 5. Seeing the <hi>nations</hi> are there said to be <hi>saved</hi> also, I believe ours is the first that shall be <hi>saved</hi> from all their <hi>oppressors and oppressions.</hi> 6. The ground of this to me is thus, because our <hi>Nobles begin to be of our selves,</hi> and our <hi>Prince or Governour to proceed from the midst of us,</hi> Jer. 30.21. that is, from the midst of Saints one is risen above us, and of the same spirit with us he is, though not in Forms of Religion, wherein the Saints do differ, yet in the power of Righteousness we all agree: yea our <hi>Prelatick brethren</hi> vowed in their Baptism to <hi>forsake the devil and all his works, the pomps and vanities of this wicked world;</hi> against which, God hath visibly appeared, plaguing the oppressing King and his proud Courtiers; yea, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that <hi>pomp and vanity</hi> the Saints have always professed, as being not sutable to the Spirit of <hi>Jesus,</hi> no, nor to the spirit of a Man: for <hi>who can see a poor Nation perishing for want of that fulness which is spent in meer superfluittes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Though Christian Kings and Nobles, bewitched with the <hi>glory of the earth,</hi> have nothing to entertain one another, but their <hi>gawdy shews, and simple gallantry;</hi> yet are some <hi>heathen Kings</hi> as much in <hi>honour with God and men,</hi> though they sit on a <hi>Carpet,</hi> and set up their <hi>throne in the boughs of trees:</hi> and so may an honest Christian Prince be as happie and honourable in <hi>a guard of Red-coats,</hi> as the most gorgeous attendance and <hi>modes of Nobles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. What a <hi>glory</hi> will this be for the <hi>nations</hi> about, to behold <hi>a man</hi> in the <hi>image and likeness of God,</hi> clothed with the <hi>robe of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118203:7"/> righteousness</hi> and <hi>garments of salvation,</hi> saving the Nation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from all that needless expence which may be spared, and setting up <hi>his throne in the hearts</hi> of his people.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Though neither Scripture nor the Spirit of Jesus will suffer any <hi>scorn or reproach</hi> to be cast on <hi>the Powers</hi> ordained by him, (as all Powers are of God, however men come by it, or men think of it) and seeing he is <hi>minister of God for good, and of wrath</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to them that resist or do evil; yet are not Kings <hi>unlimited in their power,</hi> nor <hi>unaccountable to the People,</hi> as all the people of God, <hi>Parliament and Army,</hi> have formerly protested, but even the highest in Power has been curbed and cut off by force, yet still that Force had the face of Authority on it. For the sake of the Saints I believe it was so disposed by Divine wisdom, that fools might not reproach his people for Rebellion against their <hi>Prince or Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. As the Parliament subdued the King and the Army dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Parliament, and the People had a hand in each (both Parliament and Army being the Peoples servants, as 'twas com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly voted) so the Power being now in the hands of the people of God, God will truly talk with them, if they offend; yea, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them too, if they oppress: for that's the Assyrian spoken of, <hi>Isai.</hi> 31.8. Now that by the Assyrian is some Prince or Princes of the people of God, is proved by this: <hi>Isai.</hi> 31.6. <hi>Turn ye to him from whom the children of Israel have deeply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted.</hi> Then it follows, <hi>The Assyrian shall fall by the sword,</hi> v. 8. 'Tis clear the children of Israel were not then in captivity under <hi>the Assyrian,</hi> but with their own Princes, as 'tis expressed, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.2. <hi>They oppress a man and his house, even a man and his heritage: even of late my people is risen up as an enemy: ye pull off the robe with the garment from them that pass by securely, as men averse from war. The women of my people have ye cast out of their pleasant houses, from their children have ye taken away my glory for ever.</hi> Oh how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny widows and fatherless children have perished by the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament! yea men who were averse to War, those who never so much as fought for the King, are for ever undone and rob'd of their childrens portions, called the glory of God. Now as all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118203:7"/> Oppressions in the Land were charged on the Prince of Israel; so he is called the <hi>Assyrian,</hi> who <hi>shall fall by the sword not of a mighty man, and the sword not of a mean man shall devour him,</hi> &amp;c. that is, the <hi>Parliament was a mighty man,</hi> by whom the <hi>King fell;</hi> and the Sword of the <hi>Army was as the mean man,</hi> by whom the <hi>Parliament fell.</hi> But there will be an oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Power that shall not fall by man, but by God he shall fall, by the <hi>sword of the Lord</hi> onely, by the Spirit of the Lord; this shall slay the <hi>Oppressor,</hi> but save the <hi>Power,</hi> because as God <hi>saves men as by fire;</hi> so his <hi>fire being in Zion, and his furnace in Jerusalem</hi> this shall never cease burning in the hearts of <hi>his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> till they shall cease to <hi>oppress:</hi> yea, though the <hi>Oppressor should prevail,</hi> yet the <hi>fire is in Zion</hi> still, <hi>a spirit of righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> is so kindled in the people of the Lord, and in the people of the Land, that it shall never be quenched, till <hi>a King comes to reign in righteousness, and Princes to rule in judgement. Isai.</hi> 32.1.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Therefore it is that some speak of a <hi>Publike spirit of righteousness</hi> risen of late in the world. It began first with us in <hi>England;</hi> it followed in <hi>France,</hi> though there <hi>the fire is fiercer,</hi> the <hi>flames</hi> more furious, and a <hi>greater confusion</hi> is coming on that Nation for the <hi>blood of the Saints</hi> that they have shed, whose <hi>swords</hi> are now sheathed in <hi>one anothers bowels,</hi> not for <hi>religion or righteousness</hi> sake, as 'twas with us, but meerly, as if God would massacre them all, he <hi>smites every horse among them with astonishment, and his rider with madness: but he opens his eyes on the house of Judah,</hi> and makes the changes of Government in <hi>England</hi> so milde and peaceable, that the Nations about call it a miracle, to see neither a drop of blood nor a tear shed, scarce a sigh of the people in the fall of their Princes. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.4,6. compared.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That spirit of righteousness, that <hi>publike spirit of liberty</hi> and freedom has much been <hi>embondaged</hi> in former Ages <hi>by the spirit of Antichrist</hi> in the world, as Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> well observed in his <hi>Anticavalierism,</hi> p. 31, 32, 36. for as the <hi>Priest and the Prince,</hi> the <hi>Mitre and Scepter</hi> were both supported each by other: so we read in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that <hi>the Beast carries the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118203:8"/> Whore;</hi> the <hi>Civil</hi> state bears up the <hi>Ecclesiastick;</hi> and this bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters up the other in all unrighteousness, that the <hi>Church</hi> might rule; for then the Rulers may rant. Therefore as at Babylons fall the <hi>Kings and Merchants</hi> (or Ministers) cry, <hi>Alas, alas:</hi> so 'tis like the Lord will <hi>bless the present Government,</hi> because 'tis now as 'twas never before, that is, <hi>the Ecclesiastick state is not set up with the Civil power,</hi> not sits <hi>in the throne,</hi> as formerly, and as 'tis in <hi>New-England</hi> this day. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 19.3,6,11,14. compared.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Though this <hi>spirit of publike righteousness</hi> be risen up in the <hi>Saints,</hi> yet the <hi>Saints</hi> (lying still in spiritual <hi>bondage in Babylon,</hi> in much confusion) cannot clearly see <hi>the Lord in the clouds,</hi> nor yet men aright in <hi>these things,</hi> nor the ways of God <hi>in the deep,</hi> nor the ways of men <hi>in the dark,</hi> nor those cross providences every day appearing as <hi>a wheel in a wheel,</hi> nor those <hi>whirlwindes</hi> without and within, which carry the best of men about so quick, and <hi>so high,</hi> and then <hi>down</hi> again in the <hi>dirt,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> was, that no Saint can stand or see clearly, what God will do with <hi>Man, and with Magistrates</hi> in this Nation.</p>
               <p>But though this <hi>publike spirit of righteousness</hi> be not come forth so fully in the Saints, as to <hi>reprove Kings,</hi> and to <hi>binde them in chains,</hi> as it will be (for, <hi>this honour have all the Saints;</hi> and this will not be so, till <hi>all the Saints</hi> be together <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered with God,</hi> which is the reign of Christ) yet, who knows, but that the first fruits of the Spirit begin to appear? some secret breathings after publike righteousness, some gaspings for peace, and glimpses of glory on earth; that as <hi>Judah ruleth with God, and is faithful with the Saints,</hi> Hos. 11.12. so the <hi>Saints begin to reign with God</hi> already, in that sense aforesaid, <hi>Olive-leaf,</hi> p. 7.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>publike spirit of righteousness</hi> in the Saints so <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Nations,</hi> is not by Resisting, but by Reproving the Powers; nor yet by reproaching them, but by strong rebukes. Indeed formerly the Saints have resisted (even for outward Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) unto blood, both King and Parliament can witness it also; but all that will be hereafter (I hope) shall be onely by sweet reproofs, or strong rebukes.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118203:8"/>
               <p>'Tis true, some Spiritual men and Ministers have formerly acted in secret against the Civil Powers, as Prelates with the Irish for the King, and Presbyters with the Scots for the Parliament; but our Independent brethren never did so, nor would act (I believe) onely they spake conscientiously as they conceived, <hi>in zeal</hi> for their God, for the <hi>good</hi> of men, for the <hi>honour of Saints,</hi> for the <hi>safety of the nation,</hi> yea for the <hi>glory of the Government and Governours</hi> thereof in the <hi>reign of Christ,</hi> which though they <hi>mistake</hi> in, and have some <hi>mis-apprehensions</hi> in that <hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual mystery,</hi> yet (not acquainted with Mysteries of State, nor minde of God in all things) they spake simply, plainly, and openly, not intending any secret designe, nor commotion among men, but discharging their conscience in reproving the untruths and evils of Men. But God will turn all things to good.</p>
               <p>Yet let me say this, not against my brethren, but for the Lord in them, That though Christ called <hi>Herod a fox,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Nero a lion,</hi> yet that was by a publike spirit in both; which as the Saints cannot now shew; so I deny not (as I said before) but there may be a <hi>beginning</hi> of the <hi>same</hi> spirit of <hi>publike righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness</hi> and <hi>reproof too of Kings</hi> in the people of God this day.</p>
               <p>Neither do I speak in this against the Powers, but for the Lord in them, who hath done all, and <hi>ordained</hi> them, and <hi>set them on high,</hi> not to <hi>throw them down</hi> again, I hope, but to <hi>exalt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self</hi> in them, and <hi>all the Saints</hi> with him, and <hi>all the nation</hi> with them <hi>in Peace</hi> and perfect freedom at last.</p>
               <p>And as my brethren meant <hi>no hurt</hi> to the <hi>Powers,</hi> so the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> intend <hi>no harm</hi> to them; (all is for peace and love;) not to <hi>imprison,</hi> but onely to <hi>restrain</hi> them, not from their <hi>private li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> but from that <hi>publike concourse</hi> and <hi>popular salutes,</hi> which might rather <hi>oppress</hi> their spirits, then <hi>refresh</hi> them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are <hi>retired for a time</hi> with <hi>John into Patmos,</hi> which was not a violent banishment, (as most interpret) but a voluntary yeelding to the hand of the Lord leading him thither, not onely from the <hi>fellowship of his Church,</hi> but from the <hi>exercise of his Apostleship,</hi> that he might <hi>retire into the Lord,</hi> and have larger <hi>Revelations</hi> in the Spirit, both of those <hi>spiritual wickednesses</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118203:9"/> reigning in the last times, and of that <hi>spiritual glory</hi> to be reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Saints, and to the Nation also. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24.</p>
               <p>But because we spake of those <hi>reproofs and strong rebukes</hi> before, let me tell you in a word, There is no <hi>way for Peace,</hi> nor shall War ever cease, but onely by this: <hi>he shall rebuke many people;</hi> then <hi>shall they beat their swords into plow-shares,</hi> &amp;c. Isai. 2.4.</p>
               <p>How will God rebuke, but by men? and by what men more, then by the Saints? yea, by the People also, who shall rebuke their Princes and Oppressors, as 'tis plain, <hi>Isai.</hi> 19.20.</p>
               <p>But how will God in the Saints rebuke the Powers of the earth? Why by the <hi>Spirit of Jesus</hi> in them, which shall make them of <hi>so quick understanding in the fear of the Lord, that they shall judge, not after the sight of the eyes, nor reprove af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the hearing of the ear.</hi> Here's a secret, that the Saints in the Lord shall judge men whom they never see, and reprove what they never hear of by them. <hi>Isai.</hi> 11.3. How can this be? 'Tis answered. vers. 4. <hi>With righteousness he shall jude the poor and reprove with equity for the meek of the earth:</hi> that is, the Lord in his people is said to judge the poor. To <hi>judge</hi> here, is <hi>rightly to consider</hi> of their cause, or condition. And mark 'tis with <hi>righteousness and equity they reprove,</hi> and for the <hi>meek of the earth,</hi> who sit still and are quiet in all their sufferings; yet can they see in God, and speak to God what is done among men, and by men cunning and cruel: therefore <hi>he shall smite the earth with the rod of his mouth, and with the breath of his lips shall he slay the wicked,</hi> vers. 4. that as Christ with the breath of his lips made <hi>a band of souldiers to fall down backwards,</hi> Joh. 18.3,6. and as <hi>Peter</hi> by the word of his mouth slew the wicked hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, even two at once, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.5,10. so I believe 'twill be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that such a <hi>power of reproof</hi> shall appear <hi>in the Saints,</hi> that they shall smite and <hi>slay men</hi> with a words speaking.</p>
               <p>For <hi>the hand of the Lord shall be known towards his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and his indignation toward his enemies,</hi> who oppose his appearance in righteousness. <hi>Isai.</hi> 66.14. How shall the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of God</hi> be made known against them? Why his <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes shall be with flames of fire,</hi> vers. 15. Where's this <hi>fire?</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:118203:9"/> but <hi>in Zion, and his furnace in Jerusalem,</hi> Isai. 31.9.</p>
               <p>So then, 'tis not so much by <hi>speaking</hi> in <hi>publike</hi> unto men, or against men, but the Saints shall so see in God mens e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states and spirits, that this shall be not onely a <hi>strong reproof,</hi> but a <hi>sure ruine</hi> of such in whom righteousness appears not: their rebukes being <hi>not verbal, but substantial and strong,</hi> yea so <hi>fiery,</hi> that all before them shall fall.</p>
               <p>I know what I say in this, by experience; and 'tis plain in the <hi>two Witnesses</hi> (who are the small number of suffering Saints under the Apostasie:) <hi>If any man will hurt them, fire proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of their mouths, and devours their enemies: and if any man will hurt them, he must in this manner be killed.</hi> In what manner? Nay the Lord knows: but as <hi>God is a spirit,</hi> so in a <hi>spiritual, secret, and unknown manner,</hi> men are confounded and killed by some poor souls, who never see nor speak with their adversaries, who neither touch them, nor think a thought of evil against them; yet by those they are killed, when once they appear against the Lord in them, and against that publike righteousness so oft professed. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.5.</p>
               <p>Lastly, 'tis clear by the Word, that <hi>Kings and Nobles must be bound in chains</hi> at last, that they shall not do what they list, as Kings and Parliaments have formerly done, but what the Saints in the Spirit shall direct and advise, not with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or contempt to the Powers on earth, but by a heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approach to God, and by that appearance of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness in Him, which they wait to be revealed in themselves and in all, for the Nations peace.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, the Saints have not been <hi>so bold of old,</hi> as to bring forth their <hi>spirits in publike,</hi> because the <hi>Power</hi> was not in <hi>the hands of the Saints,</hi> as now; who therefore must not think to <hi>play Rex,</hi> as they say, and to <hi>rant</hi> it as they please in <hi>all unrighteousness and riot,</hi> because there is a <hi>righteous genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> a <hi>pure and holy people</hi> left in the nation, that shall <hi>never leave them</hi> alone, nor rest from calling upon them in publique, or (which is worst) crying to God in secret against them, yet not against them, but for them they pray, and yet against them those prayers will be, which are for them; never was it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118203:10"/> worse with <hi>King and Parliament,</hi> then when so many prayers were made; then all those prayers turned against them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Power of righteousness could not arise in either.</p>
               <p>And this is the last reason, why of late times some Saints have been taken up into the civil state, and others to speak so much of civil things in their most spiritual discourses, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God is <hi>going up</hi> now in <hi>higher discoveries</hi> of himself even in <hi>low things of the earth:</hi> for as there is a <hi>new heaven and new earth</hi> (as I said) <hi>wherein dwelleth righteousness,</hi> so not new <hi>forms of religion,</hi> but a power of <hi>righteousness</hi> is expected <hi>newly to arise</hi> in the Nation, not onely in the <hi>Ecclesiastick,</hi> but in the <hi>Civil state,</hi> in <hi>Church and Commonwealth,</hi> that's the new Heaven and new earth waited for, when the Civil state shall be wholly spiritual.</p>
               <p>Therefore 'tis a poor low thing what <hi>some Ministers</hi> talk of, that men must now preach of nothing but <hi>Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and run <hi>sixteen yeers backwards,</hi> (as one phraseth it) <hi>into old Puritanism again.</hi> This is a prety thing indeed (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the world is on fire like Sodom) to <hi>look back</hi> with Lots wife, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or not <hi>forget what is behind</hi> with Paul, <hi>when the price of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus is not onely</hi> before us, but <hi>neerer to us then</hi> ever (the falling away being full, and Christ ready to come, and the face of God <hi>beginning to appear</hi> on our foreheads.)</p>
               <p>I will not speak of many things now to be mentioned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men: the mystery of God, the reign of Christ, the ruine of Antichrist, the restitution of all things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is this nothing but faith and repentance? yet not to leave this, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though the Apostle would.</p>
               <p>First, Was not faith and repentance but the beginnings of Christ, as the margin reads? <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1,2. and are we not called <hi>to go on to perfection?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, 'Twas once said, <hi>we walk by faith and not by sight,</hi> but where will this be, when we shall <hi>see God, and his face, as his servants shall in new Jerusalem?</hi> and that's on earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.4. surely he is stark blind who hath <hi>not seen God</hi> already, rising in <hi>the Nation, in Parliament and Army</hi> before, and I <hi>hope
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118203:10"/> higher hereafter in the present Powers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Is there not a time, that <hi>Repentance shall be hid from mine eyes?</hi> Hosea 13.14. is not this spoken of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of the dead? which though <hi>Paul</hi> had not attained to, yet he and all the Prophets and Apostles spake that it should come, a rising of the <hi>dead Men</hi> of Christs <hi>dead body,</hi> of the <hi>dry bones</hi> out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> of the <hi>first Resurrection,</hi> which some <hi>blessed and holy ones shall have their part in</hi> before their brethren, though not fully till the whole body of the Saints rise together: yet some are as the foolish child that sticks in the wombes mouth, <hi>Hosea</hi> 13.12. that is, they are coming forth of the flesh, but there they stick and suffer for it like fools, yet are they (as I said) coming forth out of the wombe of darkeness, defilement, and blood, wherein they have long laine, or rather, the Lord in them, who has been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for a <hi>long time to lye down in weakness, in low forms, and height of flesh:</hi> but now he will <hi>rise up in spirit and power,</hi> bring down the <hi>purest forms,</hi> and <hi>proudest flesh,</hi> and appear himself; first as <hi>man of warre,</hi> breaking down all the powers of Heaven, and oppressors on Earth.</p>
               <p>I have been silent saith he, of long time holden <hi>my peace and been still, and suffered Kings and Nobles</hi> to have their wills, now I'll have mine, saith God, and I will <hi>exalt my self alone,</hi> as a <hi>Man of war:</hi> This is proper for the Civil state. <hi>Isa.</hi> 42.13.</p>
               <p>That which follows is of more spiritual and inward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerment, <hi>he shall cry like a woman in travail,</hi> to bring forth his glory in our flesh: but our flesh (as Christs) must first suffer the <hi>pangs</hi> of childbearing, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.2. or God in us, vailed in our flesh will <hi>cry, yea, roare</hi> before his glory be revealed with power, in this he <hi>destroys and devours at once</hi> all our fleshly strength and weaknesses too in himself, <hi>making waste mountains and hills,</hi> high men and things, <hi>mountains</hi> of imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, <hi>strong holds</hi> of carnal reasonings, and <hi>every high thought that exalts it self against the knowledge of God.</hi> When this is done, the prophesie is finished, and my work is ended.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="epigraph">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118203:11"/>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will encamp about my house, because of the Army, because of him that pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth by, and because of him that return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; and no oppressor shall pass thorow them any more: for now I have seen with mine eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <bibl>Zech. 9.8.</bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>THat which is to <hi>heighten the spirits of the English, &amp;c.</hi> shall be next, if God will. In the mean while, if the <hi>Assyrian</hi> (or any forrain Force) shall dare to <hi>tread on our borders,</hi> we shall <hi>raise against him seven shepherds, and eight principal men,</hi> a sufficient strength (in the Lord) by land and sea. However, <hi>This Man shall be the Peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 13. line 3. for <hi>for,</hi> read <hi>against.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>